[SPEAKER_01]: The other day, you were talking about experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: You used the example of experience as looking... looking...
[SPEAKER_01]: Experience is like looking into the mirror.
[SPEAKER_01]: Remember, you were explaining, it's like a mirror.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like a mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I... Well, I do remember, but I don't remember the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, I forgot the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's basically about...
[SPEAKER_00]: Ah, no, not like a mirror, but more... okay, yes, like a mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you can't see your ex's form directly, but you can recognize, or what you can experience, is the appearance of it, which is basically like a mirror image of that which is mirrored.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can only... wherever you look, it will be looking at that mirror.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you can't look away from the mirror, or from that reflection, and see the thing that's being reflected.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you can get is the reflected of the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, your nāmarūpa is basically the reflect... as the only thing that arises, it's the all, the all, the arisen thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, that's because of which...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, matter is that because of which this nāmarūpa arises, which means it's because of that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see, when you say that matter, that already belongs to that
[SPEAKER_00]: The designation belongs to that nāmarūpa, which means it belongs to that reflected image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you all... the only way to know that matter is there, is to discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't access it through the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't appear directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, by fully understanding nāmarūpa, you then discern that nāmarūpa is because of that which does not appear, but is there as a necessary condition.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that which appears...
[SPEAKER_00]: If anything ever appears, it will appear within nāma-rūpa, which means that's the only way to appear, which means that's what appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that appearance will not be there if there is no matter to support the appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can never see the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when you think about the matter, you think within the realm of designation, which means your thinking is part of that nāma-rūpa.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when that statement sort of says,
[SPEAKER_01]: As it's about conceivings, whatever you conceive, it's always other than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I think that Sutta, if I remember correctly in the context, he was just... he wasn't dealing with these on the subtle level, you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was just basically saying that whatever Pūrṭhujana conceives, things end up being differently.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you could say...
[SPEAKER_00]: But conceiving in itself, basically, like Mūla Parīyā's Sutta, it's already...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's already a form of distortion, no matter how subtle the conceiving is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You conceive...
[SPEAKER_00]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you have the appeared... Well, you have the appearance of the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Based on that, you can discern that that appearance is obviously the appearance of that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even saying that that matter, that actually it's part of that appearance, that designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can't
[SPEAKER_00]: Go beyond the appearance or look sideways and then find that which is the cause for that appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only way to know that there is matter behind appearance is because of that which appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: So the matter can never be accessed directly, as appearance can.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you're going to have is appearance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or whatever you think about matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That small apāraya sutta, basically, it's that appearance that you then conceive to be that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You conceive it to be in that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You conceive it to be out of that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you conceive the matter through not understanding appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, the fact that, like, if you were to... if you were to test... if you were to assume that this appearance is in the matter,
[SPEAKER_00]: You fail to see that that thought in the matter is already part of that appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, you don't take it like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You take it to stand for that which that matter is, because of which this appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: So I need to replay this sentence a few times.
[SPEAKER_00]: But basically, it's quite essential.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can see it to be art.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or in and out, or both, or to be mine, or whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever permutation can do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of those things, it's irrelevant whether you conceive it in or out, to be mine, to be for me, to be I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, you're conceiving relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you're conceiving relationship, you are putting the appearance and the matter, because of which appearance is, you are putting them on the same footing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... by comparing them, by relating them, not necessarily comparing them, but
[SPEAKER_00]: By relating them, you are basically concealing the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because even that thought of, oh, this is from the matter, it's apart from the matter, it's in the matter, it's out of the matter, it's because of the matter, that thought of that matter, it's part of that appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you take it to stand for the matter because of which appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you conceived it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You gave it life that it doesn't actually have.
[SPEAKER_00]: You gave it being that it doesn't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you made it exist, just through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you if you thoroughly understand appearance, as as as as again...
[SPEAKER_00]: The illustration I gave of the mirror in front of you, and the thing that appears is behind you, it's obviously not perfect, because, you know, you always assume you can just turn your head, but you can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: In this case, you can't turn your head or look somewhere where you will access that matter, because all you can ever access will be the appearance, because that's what appears, that's what accessing is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then means that this matter is always below your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: And fully discerning that, will make you then completely relinquish any notion of belonging in regards to anything that appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, well, everything appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: 500 years it's appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: The nature is to appear, disappear and persist without changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you abandon the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through seeing that it's fully undermined by the four great elements, for example, in this example.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they can never... you can never access the Four Great Elements, yet your entire life, your entire existence is... it's like directly founded upon them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, even when you think, oh, I can't access the Four Great Elements, you can be consuming the Four Great Elements, if you think that that thought stands for that which Four Great Elements is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it can't stand, because that thought has appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's part of the appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the discernment can pertain.
[SPEAKER_00]: The knowledge can be directed towards that which does not appear,
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the ultimate determination of your entire experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just basically changing the direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you never arrive at that because of which this appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that will make it appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you just change the direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of for me, it's opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It comes from elsewhere.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's enough for dispassion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any appearance,
[SPEAKER_00]: Any experience?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's the opposite of for me, like towards you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arises for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whether you take it or leave it, it's up to you, but it's for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: My eyes, my sights, it's all for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, now you take it completely against that direction and you go the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arises from that which you cannot even conceive in your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't think of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it is that because of which
[SPEAKER_00]: And see, even when I'm talking about it like this, that's obviously the limits of the designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even when I'm talking about it, like, you know, like I'm saying, oh, it's inexpressible, but I just expressed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this is the nature of designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you should not mystify that because of which your appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: You should discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the Buddha said, when the four great elements change, and the four great elements, they find the footing
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I think about Earth...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you can do about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by recognizing that the appearance is all you have, it will make you stop assuming that you can actually access the great elements, or access anything, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even access the five aggregates, because if you were to be able to access them, in that sense, you would be dead wrong now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you're not.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't be.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're just constantly maintaining that assumption that basically feeds the conceivings, and it's because of the conceivings.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just... you just maintain the vicious circle that's completely detritious, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's unnecessary in any shape or form.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the recognition of the... of the Five Aggregates as being inaccessible to you, means, okay, you change the direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're not for you anymore, because you can't... you can't uphold them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not in their control.
[SPEAKER_00]: And they're not in your control because they are determined by that which you can't even think, let alone see, taste, or touch.
[SPEAKER_01]: Completely behind you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely underneath, below your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are the reasonable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are, sorry, you are the
[SPEAKER_01]: The result.
[SPEAKER_00]: The result of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you can say that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the simultaneous presence your whole life.
[SPEAKER_00]: The simultaneous presence of that means these things are present because I'm still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because my aggregates are still there, means the elements are still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: The consciousness in regard to them is still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all of that is indirect to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: What you have direct in front of you is nāma in regard to rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what about these things, this body and name and form externally, that the arahant experiences?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's slightly, slightly different, different approach from this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... Because when you're talking about this body...
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to remove all the assumptions, all the concealings, and you recognize that this very body that you... well, the appearance of this very body is comprised of those four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the four great elements can be discerned in regard to that appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's all... that's absolutely fine, as long as you don't start... Well, there wouldn't be a discernment, but basically, as long as you don't start then regarding that discernment as that... those elements because of which this body is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the discernment of the elements, four great elements, and the appearance of the body as a result of the four great elements, they're both appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're on the level of appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: They share the nature of appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're on a different level of generality, obviously.
[SPEAKER_00]: The body is a particular manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: The four great elements are notions of four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they can accurately stand for the four great elements if you don't conceive four great elements through those notions.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was in the relation to the other talk we spoke recently about the abstraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: When things cease to be abstract, they stand for that which they are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your thought will stand for that element, will be an accurate representation, because that's all it can be, a representation of four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, for an arahant who is free from concealing, all that's left is this conscious body here, this matter paired with consciousness externally, and all the name and forms externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: All the things that arise, name and form, basically all of the appearance, externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, the direction of internal mind towards me,
[SPEAKER_00]: has changed and now it's all external, even your utmost personal thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the external appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: This conscious body, this conscious body... Means, basically, the arrangement of the consciousness and the elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still operating.
[SPEAKER_00]: The arrangement is... you can't, like, you can't just... you can't even conceive anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: On a higher structural... Well, not on a higher, on a probably more... on an inner test, on a more... on a deeper... below your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in a way, it's more general, but, no, more generally, it pertains to things that would appear more generally.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more immediate.
[SPEAKER_00]: The way it appears, this conscious body, when it appears as a thought, that thought doesn't conceive it to be that conscious body, to be in the conscious body, or from the conscious body, or apart from, or for me, or mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't conceive.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have a thought as a mirrored representation of the conscious body present there, because of which you can still discern that the conscious body is present there, because the conscious body is still present there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of the appearance in regard to it, that's external to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, not even to you anymore, because that would imply a certain relationship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's external to me, which would imply internal.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's just external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Internal becomes external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just less external than external-external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because internal is usually mind, dear, appropriated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that internal dimension of putujana stays.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just now seen as external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And things that were external were seen as externally external.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because we're talking about today, about putting the structure of existence into the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, the structure is in the right order.
[SPEAKER_00]: The structure is in the structure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just stop concealing the wrong order on top of the existing order of the structure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's doing the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, in a way, yeah, that means not conceiving, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the order of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, let's, let's put aside the four great elements, because they might be a bit too subtle.
[SPEAKER_00]: But back onto the conscious body, right here.
[SPEAKER_01]: The senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you can, as I was telling you today, you can actually touch your eyeball.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Close your eyelids and you can feel the shape of the planet.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it is that flesh that you're touching, that ball that you're touching with your fingers.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is that because of which there is a whole life of vision, of sights, things you see, desire and lust in regard to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Fear, in regards to things you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Grief, in regards to things you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: The whole world, in regards to things you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the same goes for every sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, if you were to touch an apple, that head torch, your eyeball, it's all... it obviously all shares the nature of the matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all material.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's this particular matter, that pertains to your body, then it's also paired with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And obviously, you can't see that consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the fact that you can discern that it's purely consciousness because you see as a result of that fleshy eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't see as a result of an apple, or a cup, or a table.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see as a result of this eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the only difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the particular arrangement of that matter enables you to see the forms because the consciousness is there with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You... there is no further... like, you can't take this to further... to a greater analysis to explain, because, as I said, consciousness doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can talk about it, but most likely you'll end up conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll end up giving it that which it doesn't have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But what you can do is recognize that it's only the passion in regard to I and forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Lust in regard to I and forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ill will in regard to I and forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: Delusion in regard... That's all it matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you have to do
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a fun way to regard it, you don't... you stop cultivating... you stop giving possibility for lust to arise in regard to I am forms.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: When that lust is removed, then that's all that needs to be done.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then what is left is this conscious body, this fleshy eye, this fleshy nose, this fleshy tongue, that is still out there below my feet with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I know that because things still appear for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, when those aggregates break apart, that's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: We're going to be mindful of the... that which doesn't appear, yet is the basis of your appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, you couldn't be mindful of that which doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be mindful of the appearance in regard to that because of which appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the more accurately mindful you are, less conceiving the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that which doesn't appear, well, you just made it appear through the statement.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is that which doesn't appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... you... you can't not have a state... you can't not have a designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't not have nāma in regard to rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what people expect to access rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or they assume that they have access to rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then my nāma is kind of optional.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rūpa is revealed through the designation of nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's inseparable, nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that revelation is very inaccurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's conceived.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you have to do is sort of make it accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop conceiving it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Purify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all you're going to have is nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: As the Buddha said, this conscious body and name and form externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what's left for an arahant.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even an arahant doesn't remove name in regard to form, or doesn't access form and then name falls off.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's name and form.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just discerning properly, through that name, you can then remove the footing for the form, in terms of conceiving, so you can liberate yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So mindfulness in the... let's say mindfulness of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you think, when you have a thought of mindfulness of the body, you're not actually directly mindful of those four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't access them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're mindful of their appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or rather, you're mindful of appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's what appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not their appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: The appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the appearance is because the four great elements are still there, standing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that the body that should be noticed in satipaṭṭhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's...
[SPEAKER_01]: Which?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean by that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that's what you've got to understand.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what body that you're seeing, being mindful of, is the body that appeared.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're properly mindful, you will understand mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: You will understand appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would stop conceiving.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you, even through the practice of mindfulness, still think, no, this is that body.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's comprised of the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means the appearance is made of it, but that's all you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the mindfulness, if you start being mindful correctly, it's not mine, not for me, not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: As I said, you can't be mindful of the actual elements behind the body, or underneath it, but you can disown the body, which then will become an accurate representation of the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And their ultimate nature is, they are not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cannot be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can... they... they're not even possible to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you start emulating that in regard to appearance, and eventually, it will... it will stand for... for how things actually are, which means you've been around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you can't undo it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's proper mindfulness has to be paired with that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: Absolutely.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right view comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the mindfulness cannot be the right one, if there's no right view, no matter how general that mindfulness is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The right view always comes first, which is why you have to... and it makes everything else right, done, done upon it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like this, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: In the Ānāpānasati Sutta, there's a one section in the beginning, it says, calming... it's always translated, calming the bodily formation.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the bodily formation?
[SPEAKER_01]: The breath, breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Ānāpānasati Sutta, Kāyā-saṃphara, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: He, while breathing in, he experiences the whole body, or the whole breath, that people say the breath of body, but he experiences while he's breathing, the whole body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the next, next sentence says, like, while breathing, yeah, he breathes calming the body formation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, if the body formation is breathing, he's just, he couldn't have said calming the breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then, he could have said that, but then it wouldn't serve... it wouldn't be seen as saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: It wouldn't serve for the recognition and cultivation of the simultaneous principle of saṅkhara and sankhārta-dharmak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Full understanding of the principle means arahanty.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if he just said, just calm your breath, you won't be seeing body dependent upon the action of breathing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, this...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think... And the point... the point with that sentence
[SPEAKER_00]: You take on mindfully an act of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the same sense, eh... what is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: The turner, the wheel turner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Turns the wheel like this, turns the wheel like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You breathe in like this, you breathe...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that you're trying to control it, in terms of, eh... stop it or force it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The breathing is there, but you kind of... like, imagine the horses that are already running, but then you join in and you take the reins.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't interfere with their running, but you do take their aims.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you might slow it down or something, but they still go in the direction and you're not changing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you take on, mindfully, the act of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, and then you can influence, through the existing act of breathing, you can, okay, prolong the breath, shorten the breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: The point is, you're mindful of the breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That experience, being mindful of the breathing, because breathing is bodily.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, even just the thought of breathing already implies the experience of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's in there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're thinking about breathing, when you're breathing, through that, you're already implying a form of experience of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that experience of the body is determined by your active engagement in breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you recognize it because the breathing, the body is there and obviously body is bound with the breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean that... it doesn't necessarily mean cause and effect, like breathing results in body.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means they're inseparable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: They always occur together, never apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable to have them apart.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't conceive the breathing without a body implied in that act.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: No matter, even if it's the utmost abstraction, if you think breathing, it implies the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, in the time, it's... it's a body with... it's a body with saṅkhāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's bound up with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then you recognize, okay, because this is inseparable from... this experience of the body, right here, now, separate from breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to think about your act of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But this body here, it's that body that is inseparable from breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, any form of experience of the body, it will be the body that implies breathing, inasmuch breathing implies the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, through calming down the mindful act of breathing... Oh, no!
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that body, that abstract body, you can say even like that, that is implied in my thought of breathing, that abstract body is this body right here, right there, and their relationship is external.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that body that you think of, when you look through the act of breathing, is that body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, through affecting, through calming down the act of breathing, calming down those thoughts in regard to the act of breathing, actually, you are pertaining, you are gradually affecting the body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that relationship is external.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thoughts that you have in regard to breathing and the body,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's assumed in that breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not in your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: That thought is the appearance of a thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that thought, that thought that has the tacit implication of a body in regard to breathing, that body there is the body that's right here, right there, right now, sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you think breathing and that abstract body that appears, that body is the body that you can access through your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not necessarily through the thoughts of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's this conscious body and name and form externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: The thoughts of breathing are the name and forms externally that imply that body, this conscious body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead of maintaining the the the connection of my body, my thoughts, you actually pull it out and you recognize, no, it's the conscious body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when I think about it, that's also externally in regard to the conscious body.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no internal dimension that is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through cultivating the act of breathing, the thoughts of breathing, the mindfulness of breathing, you start discerning a phenomenon of body within that act of breathing, that is actually this body right here, right now, just seen from a different view at the same time.
[SPEAKER_01]: The body that appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, don't, don't, yeah, don't worry.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a different approach.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't, don't try and mix it, the elements and that because of which it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yeah, if you start seeing it at the same time, if a thing is present twice or seen at the same time from two points of view, so to speak, none of them can be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because mine, me, I am, requires that singularity.
[SPEAKER_00]: I look from here towards there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But now you recognize the thing is present, seen from there, and experienced right here, at the same time, which one is yours?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you realize none of them can be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, put your attention on the experience of the body right here, right now, and then start breathing, and through that breathing, discern the body, that then you start basically, right, discerning as, oh, the body that I'm, this, this, this abstract phenomenon of the body that I'm discerning through my breathing, actually stands for this very body that I'm experiencing right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But their relationship is external.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can spread it with a thought of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That then you just conceive to be, oh, this is this body right here, right now, through that internal connection.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, my thought is this body, comes from this body, it's this body, in the body, out of the body, from the body, it's for me, it's mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you recognize the thought of the body as an arisen phenomenon externally,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then see it standing for that body out there.
[SPEAKER_01]: For that body out there?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Out where?
[SPEAKER_01]: What do you mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Out where?
[SPEAKER_00]: Out there, right here.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that fleshy eye, for that nose, for the tongue.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, fleshy eye, it's a designation, it's an appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: That stands for the fleshly eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you assume, oh, it's my fleshly eye.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you see that that fleshly eye will not be known, if there is no external appearance of a thought, fleshly eye, phenomena, without, it's just inconceivable, inseparable from.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it can't be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then it just becomes all external.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's all out there, just there, right here, or yonder, whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: None of it is mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to keep constantly attending to this body right here, right now, because this body is right here, right now, and you have no choice about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: All you want to do is stop misconceiving it, or misconceiving things that appear in regard to this body right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, mindfulness of breathing, through actively engaging in an act of breathing, you start discerning the body, the phenomenal body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which then you can go, this is my body, this is the same as this body, this is the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can start seeing this body, it's basically that representation that we spoke earlier, of the body present right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's one way of looking at it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can then just be mindful of the present body, conscious body, right here, right now.
[SPEAKER_00]: In many... well,
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't really imagine it, because if you would imagine it accurately, it wouldn't be imagination.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would stand for how things are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever arises is seen from two points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Always.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just have one point of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So it's always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Twice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not twice.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will be one, too.
[SPEAKER_00]: As a presence, it's double.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, explain that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can try, but I can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can see that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, everything's seen from two different points of view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no, like everything already is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arises.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are two points of view to every experience, simultaneously present, which is why you can then develop the assumption of one point of view, which is me.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to see that you're the center of your sense of self,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always determined by something else different than that sense of self.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's two things at present.
[SPEAKER_00]: The central sense of self and that which determines it.
[SPEAKER_00]: At the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Akālika.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not pertaining to time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no time in between.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whichever point of view you took to be yours, within that you discern
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, no matter what point of view you take to be yours, simultaneously to that, it's determined by that which cannot be yours at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't have both things at the same time, because that would require a third point of view, that's more general to these two points, but that's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't help but have a point of view
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, sorry, you can't help but attend one point of view, but through that you discern another direction, that it's not the same direction, that it determines this direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is a direction of the conscious body, and there is a direction of the name and form externally.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can discern both of them simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you will have to be attending one on account of the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you attend conscious body, you'll be discerning never-forming standard.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you attend never-forming standard, you'll be discerning conscious body through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that's all you can ever have, if you contemplate it long enough, you'll stop assuming one single unifying point of view, that it's neither here nor there, nor both, nor whatever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's only maintained through a simple not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not discerning of the arrangement of things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, by not fully understanding that things cannot be yours,
[SPEAKER_00]: You maintain the notion of their mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, right here, right now, while you're thinking about what I've just said, your body is seated present with the conscious and spared with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Those are two simultaneous things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no matter how hard you're thinking, whatever you're thinking, through that, the discernment of this conscious body present right here, right now, is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because
[SPEAKER_00]: This conscious body right here is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And in this particular instance, it's basically the reason why you're able to think in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why any dhamma can also be a saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any of the aggregates can also be a determination.
[SPEAKER_01]: As we say, watching the breath.
[SPEAKER_00]: It depends what you attend, then the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to discern the opposite of where your attention is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if I'm watching the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you're watching the body...
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see that it's been... the termination is the breath.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I'm not looking at the breath, are I?
[SPEAKER_00]: I guess so, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can see it in the background.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if I'm looking at the breath, I can see the body...
[SPEAKER_00]: In the practice of ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: But just in terms of that practice...
[SPEAKER_00]: Watching the breath and having... Well, in terms of that practice, yeah, you want to be, you want to be doing mindfulness of breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You want to be actively, because it's a form of an act, that you want to tune yourself into.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you're breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you recognize, through this very act, you start discerning the implicit notion of the body, present right there, right then.
[SPEAKER_00]: If something were to happen while you're breathing there and discerning that body through that body, if those elements that that body is comprised of would change, disappear, be affected by some other external factor, you realize that all acts
[SPEAKER_00]: That you're still mindfully engaging your breathing, cannot remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yet, its foundations are completely inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if something happens to grey elements, you can't possibly continue breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly continue discerning the body through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through contemplating like that, you have abandoned the very nature of action, of intentional action.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an act.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a neutral act, which is why we praise it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you cultivate it long enough, you develop mindfulness that then won't be disturbed by any other form of act that are not unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, they have to be abandoned beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you're sitting, walking, eating, talking, none of it then becomes... well, none of them... none of that continues to imply
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, the notion of permanence, the notion of control in regard to things.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you abandon your own intention, it ceases to be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because through practicing of intentional attending to breathing, and breathing in like this, breathing out like that, discerning the body through that, and then seeing that if that thing changes, if that determination is swept away, none of your present acts can remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: You do that long enough,
[SPEAKER_00]: None of the notions of I am, and this is me, this is for me, can remain standing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will just evaporate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you just breathe, and through breathing, simultaneously, you discern the presence of the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, you can start attending to the body right here, right now, but then, obviously, you're not mindful of the breathing anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can be mindful of the body, but then, you're not doing ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, it's just one wave of developing mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you want to stick to ānāpānasati, you just continue breathing in while you're descending body through that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you realize, oh, if I... if I calm down this breathing, this active engagement, that body will calm down.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I slow it down, the experience of that body through that slowing down of breath will be affected as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you can contemplate the four noble truths or any other thing, as the Buddha says, through that breathing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have refined your active engagement with the action, with the nature of action.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not distracted, you're doing it mindfully, and through that you're discerning the present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because no matter what you're doing, whether you're sweeping leaves, walking, sitting, talking, there is an implication to your body present right there, right there, simultaneously.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if that body is not present right there, right then, simultaneously, you wouldn't be able to be engaging in these acts actively at the very time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just that you don't... you're not aware of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not aware of the presence of the body, while you engage actively in this task, because your attention is unmindful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you maintain the notion of procreation through that very thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you start discerning the body, and then you recognize that, well, there is no room for me and I am, in that act.
[SPEAKER_00]: That act, this act, these intentions, these choices I'm making, next moment,
[SPEAKER_00]: These are all possible because there is this... well, there is the implication you can see through of the body right while those acts are present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's that thought that is crystallizing of that body that's revealed through
[SPEAKER_00]: Mindful engagement with these acts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, the body is always present.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a phenomenon of present body through these acts.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that body is that which this body is, when I think about it, separate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, whether you think about the body directly or indirectly, you stop conceiving it as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see it as that thing out there, because of which you're able to move and act and choose.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you start seeing your own choices as a result, because of that present conscious body out there, right there, at the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, next time you make a choice, or rather, when you have practiced this efficiently, then when the choices are being made, even that, the most personal thing, I want this over that, ceases to induce the notion of personality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's understanding, it's seeing through and through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be able to think unrelated things to your body?
[SPEAKER_00]: Just think something completely out of the imagination?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, no matter how disconnected, unrelated your thoughts might be, the nature of the thought is bound with the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: In as much, the body is bound with the mind, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hence, it only depends what you attend, it will be determined by the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you wouldn't be able to even think about body, talk about body, if the mind doesn't designate it at the time as body, as that, as that physical in regard to itself, or that less mental in regard to itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, before you're saying that, those thoughts in regard to body would stop conceiving, would stop making you assume that that is actually that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's still thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all you can have is thoughts and thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the mind comes first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you know a cup as a cup?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you know matter as matter?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even saying it matter, thinking it matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's already a designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all you have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just
[SPEAKER_00]: Designations are different levels of generality, pertaining to different things.
[SPEAKER_00]: What's the designation?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you want to do is make sure that when it comes to designation of the body, in regard to body, whether peripherally, whether directly, when you're attending it, you don't conceive that that is that matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't conceive that that is what those great elements are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it will always remain below your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: There will always remain that because of which this appearance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: And this appearance, in this case, is the designation of this body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right here, right now, that I'm seeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can touch parts of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only thing you can have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even in terms of if you think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just stop conceiving that to be standing for this external world of four varied elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's another thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what you have is thoughts in regards to thoughts, but those thoughts can be discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, they are because of the four great elements that I'm thinking right here, right now, which is all I can do, but I'm not conceiving to be those four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the important thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you only say, oh, all you have is your thoughts, then you, well, you'll fall into a very obvious, naive form of idealism.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, whatever you think it's in your head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, whenever I think it's in my head, you assume your head to be material in regard to your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, even that is your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't even intelligibly say whatever you're thinking, it's in my head, because that's in my head, which is in my head, which is in my head, which is in my head.
[SPEAKER_00]: Indefinitely.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you realize, the notion of my head is because it's underlined by the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: There are also other notions, but the notion does not conceive
[SPEAKER_00]: ...itself to be the actual four great elements, or to be apart from them, which would imply them to be something else, or to be in them, or to be from them, or to be for me, or to be among.
[SPEAKER_00]: The notion just doesn't conceive any of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the notion for... it's known... a notion is known as a notion.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't conceive that because of which the notion is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, put it in more simpler terms, the notion is fully disowned.
[SPEAKER_00]: The notion is discerned as impossible to own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Notion is a dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: A dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: Notion is a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Notion of this, notion of that, thing, a thought, you can call it whatever you want, basically a phenomenon.
[SPEAKER_00]: Phenomenon is that which has a nature to appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: What has a nature to appear?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything has a nature to appear that you can talk about.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that have no need to appear, you can't possibly discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: Since they don't appear, you can't even think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, when you reach that understanding, abide in that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Become that understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're saying about finding the balance in, you know, finding the balance in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you... Well, you don't need to balance it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you understood, you can't undo the understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's no balance to be maintained, because you're... it's developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why you know it's developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the vision that you see, you see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: What you're talking about now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You see it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, you can... Well, you can know that it hasn't been developed sufficiently, or hasn't been developed fully.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you just have to keep repeating it and drilling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The very same inside.
[SPEAKER_01]: By investigating those dhammas, those... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding the dhammas.
[SPEAKER_00]: By understanding that which has a nature to appear, which is your thoughts, your feelings,
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intentions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your perception has an age to appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feeling has an age to appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Attention has an age to appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even your attention has an age to appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can talk about, I'm attending to this.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's indirect, it's negative in regard to what is being attended, but it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's a tension.
[SPEAKER_00]: And so, all of that is nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: The designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Name.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I said nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: The rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just said it in the same sense you said, in the same way you said nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: So rūpa is also designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's a more general designation than the designation of nāma.
[SPEAKER_00]: More fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: Direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it still pertains actually to the nature of desimation.
[SPEAKER_00]: That then stops conceiving itself to be that rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all.
[SPEAKER_00]: What is all?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's nāmarūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's all that can appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nothing else except nāmarūpa can appear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't mean that rūpa is actually
[SPEAKER_00]: The rūpa, because of which nāmarūpa is as appearance.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's only one way to correctly, accurately designate rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that way is by not having that designation stand for that rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it doesn't, if it doesn't conceive that rūpa, the designation of rūpa doesn't conceive rūpa, that's the only accurate designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's liberation.
[SPEAKER_00]: You practice that and it will be free from all conceivings, from all implications of mind, thus from all implications of I am, thus from all implications of self, myself and personality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or you can take your experience as a whole and regard... and you have kind of things... aspects of it that are more mental and aspects of it that are more material, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: But both are actually part of the designation.
[SPEAKER_00]: nāma in regard to rūpa.
[SPEAKER_00]: So what you have to do is that while they're simultaneously present,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, stop regarding the material aspect as... stop assuming the material aspect as pertaining to the actual method because of which the designation of material aspects can arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop conceiving them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because any movement of your mind, it's already pertaining to the... it appears.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's part and element.
[SPEAKER_00]: In regard to rūpa,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can know your experience as a whole, in whatever shape and form can arise, is because of the four great elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: As long as there's knowledge, well, then it won't be knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: But as long as there's thought,
[SPEAKER_00]: Does not conceive the four great elements through the thought about them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't actually assume that that's what they are, or that there's something else, or elsewhere, or both, or neither.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just don't give in to any of those.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just have a thought of four great elements, so you don't overdo it, you don't underdo it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then that thought won't be conceiving that.
[SPEAKER_00]: They won't find a footing in your experience, which means your experience will be free.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just something that needs to be repeated on and on and on, through different means.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you end up repeating the same principle, the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I call it contemplationism.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bit of a head-spinner.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's a head-spinner, if obviously you wanna be as particular as that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't have to, because there are much less particular things, sorry, much less ambiguous things that you can contemplate, that would be maintaining and obviously drilling the same principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, not for me, not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you extend that principle to the point of pertaining to the thought of not mine, not for me, not my control, then you won't leave anything excluded.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you repeat that long enough, then that thing will become apparent, because it does correspond with how things actually are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not yours, not for you, not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where do you call it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Outlet.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the Mūla Pāryāya Sutta.
[SPEAKER_00]: The monks did not rejoice in the Buddha, because they didn't understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, for example, there's elements that we're talking about today as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sensual pleasure, I mean, the sensual pleasure element and renunciation element.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the ill-will element and non-ill-will element.
[SPEAKER_01]: Cruelty element and non-cruelty element.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when one is experiencing ill-will,
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-ill will is the great.
[SPEAKER_00]: Hmm.
[SPEAKER_00]: And seeing those two things... Why is the non-ill will great?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it more?
[SPEAKER_01]: Why is it great?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it great?
[SPEAKER_01]: But it takes... doesn't take you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, no, that's why... why... why it's wholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it greater?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is it structurally greater than ill-will?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why is ill-will lower than non-ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because ill-will is determined.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it's because ill-will can only arise in regard to particular things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I was trying to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you experience ill-will, it's only in regard to something.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if it's a very general, ambiguous mood or thought, you're having ill-will in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means, ill-will is always circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because these things could have not arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: But which is more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Things that...
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry, you don't know which is more?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Can you have desire and lust or ill-will in regard to things that you've never seen, you've never heard, you've never thought of?
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just... it's inconceivable to experience desire and lust or aversion in regard to that which is never... has never manifested in any particular form.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have those... those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only have non-ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can only have non-aversion, non-lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the default mode.
[SPEAKER_00]: On a basis of non-lust, you develop lust in regard to something that's being manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you know that I can't have lust in regard to things that are not manifested, that means that whatever is manifested, it's circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if it was manifested, and has it been manifested before, if it was manifested, means it could have not been manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it certainly means, oh, it's manifested, thus it will unmanifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will cease, because it has arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly have lust for that which doesn't manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't possibly have real will for that which doesn't manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, when you do have lust or real will, you recognize, oh, it's in regard to a circumstantial thing that could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's completely treacherous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because lust would actually imply
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole notion of, oh, this is special, this is particular, this is worthy, this is valuable, this is great.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when you recognize that it's circumstantial, it, it, it, it, well, it loses its elevated state.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is important.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is important, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what it means by saying that non-ill will is greater.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more fundamental.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's more important.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there are more things that have been arisen
[SPEAKER_00]: There are more things that are manifested.
[SPEAKER_00]: And for them, which you can't have... for them, you can't have lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't have ill will, which means there is more non-ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even for people who are always angry.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're always angry at something particular, which means, on the general level, there is more non-ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why you don't do the non-ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just discern it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And because of that, you can't engage in ill will.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same, you discern that
[SPEAKER_00]: Absence of passion has an inherent characteristics of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you stop at the ten notions of passion in regard to the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: Upādāna is not the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't possibly be.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's not found anywhere else apart from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the desire and lust in regard to five aggregates that the assumption is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's greater than particular manifestation of desire and lust in regard to the particular manifestation of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: It always could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's another the contemplation is called before.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start thinking that over the things that are appearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, this could have not been and it will... this it will... it will... it will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, things that will be, will not be for me, because that circumstantialness of it, the thread of it, just pertains to the past, to the present, and the past that is present, and the future that is present as a possibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, so when the things in the future, if this wall still remains standing, arise, it's impossible for them to arise for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: As much as this present thing is also impossible to be accessed by me, it's possible to be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, you realize, oh, my whole past was actually never for me and thus it was never mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how you don't dwell in the past and you don't go in the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: By descending the present, by descending then through the present, not by stopping your thinking and refraining from thinking about your past.
[SPEAKER_00]: But by fully discerning that the thing is inaccessible now, that nature pertains in the future, and that nature pervades the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why Arahant does not... like, you know, he was in Arahant always, but when he becomes in Arahant, he doesn't have thoughts anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: I was in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I'm in Arahant, but I was in the past before.
[SPEAKER_00]: I actually was as a person.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: That whole thing is affected.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you don't have always laid in front of you past, present, future, because it will require an entity, a subject, that kind of has an overview over these three things, that are flowing in front of your eyes, as a as a slideshow or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are part of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can only have over-determined present, that is present, or under-determined present, that is present.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you can have past, that is present, if that's the direction you're looking, or if you look in the direction of possibilities, you can have the future, that is not yet present, and that's present.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a bit more complex.
[SPEAKER_00]: Complex for people who commonly think, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't think about the future, don't worry about the past.
[SPEAKER_01]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's present and you have no choice about that present.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, don't don't regard your past as yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't plan your future as belonging to you, as pertaining to you, as arising for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can know the future you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: It might not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sorry.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will not be for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: And certainly, it could have not been.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever it is, it could have been not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: Circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you make any choices, any decisions, commit any acts, based on that which is circumstantial, you can only regard those choices, those acts as yours,
[SPEAKER_00]: If you forget or if you don't fully discern the dependence of your choices upon this circumstantially arisen thing, if you remain mindful of the circumstantial nature of the arisen thing upon which you're acting and choosing and deciding, you won't be owning your choice either.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that can be only when present.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't go in hindsight and say, ah, well, because things are not mine, my decisions are not mine as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's wishful thinking.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to see that directly.
[SPEAKER_00]: While things are seen as not yours, what you're deciding upon that will not be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that limits the things you can decide.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you do see circumstantially or reasoned things as present,
[SPEAKER_00]: Simultaneously present determinations of your choices in regard to the circumstantial themes, your choices cannot be affected by lust, aversion and delusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because lust, aversion and delusion require that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it requires the opposite of circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires the special, the important, the mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you see that it can't be yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not special.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's particularly arisen on account of the basis of all of it that's not arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can't have lust towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you certainly can't have ill will towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you won't be able to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just not worthy anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is not worthy of delight, of craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not worthy.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you automatically stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even
[SPEAKER_01]: The grief that arises through abandoning this... in this realm, again, grief that arises...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's with... yeah, it's with embed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even that is circumstantial.
[SPEAKER_00]: So you surround that... You surround grief as well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because grief is grief only when it's mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: But... You stop grieving when it doesn't pertain to you anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you're renouncing sensual pleasures, that's keeping restraint.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're emulating the right order of things.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you also know, no matter what happens because of your renouncing, because of your not engaging in sensual pleasures, it can't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It'll be a good thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It'll be a good thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what Guruji said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if a person doesn't develop any wisdom, even if a monk doesn't develop any wisdom, stays a pūtugina, basically, and lives his holy life, his renunciate life, in tears, because of the pain of restraining sensuality, it's still better than giving in to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because at least he's living the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: The principle of non-lust.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because anyone can sort of... well, I wouldn't say anyone...
[SPEAKER_00]: He won't be enlightened as a result of it, but he certainly, by living the principle, yeah, he brings himself closer to the enlightenment, obviously, in lives to come.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's still better in the long run.
[SPEAKER_01]: But when you have the knowledge that...
[SPEAKER_00]: When you have the knowledge that discerns the principle that you start living beforehand, which is why sīla has to come first, then the knowledge discerns, then you basically...
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You discern, you fully understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you don't even have to keep doing it, because you are it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't have to keep emulating the principle, when you become a principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it takes over.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you can spend all emulating you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody points out to you, if you don't discern it, you won't, you will remain a tutor.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why there is no dhamma without sīla.
[SPEAKER_00]: But certainly, sīla is not dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: But dhamma is impossible to have without starting with emulation of the right principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because dhamma doesn't properly renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can very easily lead to wisdom, with very little instruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why he sees the danger in the slightest thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean he becomes neurotic, obsessed with anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means he sees the danger, he starts discerning it.
[SPEAKER_00]: The slightest deviation from the principle can be an obstacle, a massive obstacle later on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a big danger.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I won't deviate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, you know, your ship is on a course.
[SPEAKER_00]: In your mind, more or less, it's just, just, just like, I don't know, 0.01 degree.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if that course goes long enough, that 0.1 can cause you to miss the whole continent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because eventually, you pull that out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you, if you literally, if you just start emulating the principle of non-lust, non-aversion, non-delusion, non-indolence, with your body, with your speech, and with your mind, with lethal instruction from the suttas, then more than enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, you need to emulate the principle harder.
[SPEAKER_00]: With more discerned instructions, you can emulate it to a lesser extent, because then the knowledge can take root quicker.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, obviously, you become it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't mean, like, somebody will keep the precepts less, if they understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: On the contrary, they need to worry less about the precepts, when they understand, or if they have more understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will take the root quicker.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for those who don't have, who have, like, lots of faith, and they just emulate heavily, they might... they really need to, like, like, take, you know, a whole new level of emulation, and then it will take root.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even with a little knowledge, they might have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, they need to have.
[SPEAKER_00]: Without any knowledge, again, as I said, you can emulate the principle all you want, live a very wholesome life, become very authentic.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can still remain putujana if nobody points out.
[SPEAKER_00]: But today, it's kind of impossible, because today, nobody emulates the principle of wholesome living.
[SPEAKER_00]: And those who do, do it as a result of the Buddha's instruction, which means those who emulate the principle are already familiar enough with the Buddha's teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: They may not go into all the details that we just talked about, for example, conceiving and stuff, but they don't eat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it emulates...
[SPEAKER_00]: It emulates the principle and then you start discerning that that is how things actually are.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not yours, not for you, not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not possible to actually be affected by lust.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not possible to be affected by rage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not possible to be affected by delusion, ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then all the factors will follow.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a slower process than the one who is emulating the principle and actively trying to understand it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's doubled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Doubled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, basically, you fight on both fronts.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's the same emulation, it's the same...
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's the same result and it's the same emulation, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just always if somebody's just emulating the principle, but not trying to understand the principle as well, then you might have people with greater intellectual capacities.
[SPEAKER_00]: They can understand the principle with actually quite a pure emulation.
[SPEAKER_00]: i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: their sīla is not actually developed properly, but they have quite some intelligence, they can discern, and then they'll develop.
[SPEAKER_00]: But until they develop their sīla properly,
[SPEAKER_00]: This understanding of that principle will not reach to fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: That way, sotāpannas, who have, who have sīla sufficiently for sotāpatti, but are not arahants yet, they need to keep practicing nekamā, renunciation, restraint, until the principle fully permeates everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they just need to stick to the virtuous living, sotāpannas, and they'll become arahants, because they fully understood the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, the ones who didn't stick to the virtuous living, you know, they didn't compromise their understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just slowed down their progress.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like the sotāpānas in the suttas that I mentioned, or in the vinaya rules, you know, the drinking, like lay people as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: He was a sotāpāna, but he was drunk, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he wasn't keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he had faculties developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such an extent that he could discern the principle at the very little occasion where he did keep the principle, where he did live awesomely, and he discerned the principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you know, his habit and lust took him over, but the principle was discerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at most, in seven lifetimes, he would have brought the fulfillment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there's a thing that says when he's discerning the principle, he's virtuous.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the moment of death, when you can't engage in anything circumstantial, he is that principle.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's often... it's such a prominent
[SPEAKER_00]: There's kind of a role of that in the sutra, when somebody who has the right view, or who is... who's already reached the... oh, well, he might attain... if he doesn't attain the fruits of his understanding in this life, he will attain the moment of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's where the principle is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not mine, not for me, not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: The manifestation of death.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can abide in it, quite so.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can develop it before you actually go through with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Chaman died before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: He didn't mean that in a poetic, inspirational way as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's quite a fact.
[SPEAKER_00]: Die before you die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Go where the death is and abandon it yourself before it hits you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go where the death is, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Go where the death is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because death is everything opposite of my life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Death is the ultimate, not yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can think you're on death.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can think you're ready for death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only Arahant is ready for death.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's no attack, no holding of any form of life, any form of bhāva, any form of being.
[SPEAKER_00]: But for Kṭṭhṛjana, death always comes from the opposite way you're looking at.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it always comes from behind you, from behind your attention, from underneath your feet.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you can never be prepared for death.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's Kṭṭhṛjana.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's so exponent.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can, but you will still experience some anguish in regard to it, because, well, because you have left work undone.
[SPEAKER_00]: You understood the principle, but you haven't been emulating it sufficiently for it to permeate everything and make all of the, all of the patterns evaporate and disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where is it, boy?
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't sleep.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the perfectly emulating wholesome living, sīla, seeing the danger in the slightest fault, with the instruction that you already have, with the discernment that you already have, even with probably with a tenth of it, it will be enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it needs to be done, it needs to be stuck to and maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: For how long?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that can be only known in hindsight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Once you get it, once you... once... once the mind knows that it knows, then you can say, okay, well, took me only a fortnight.
[SPEAKER_00]: But took me only seven years.
[SPEAKER_00]: But took me only 17 years.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a... in a long scheme of things, it's nothing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Took me only this lifetime.
[SPEAKER_00]: Poof!
[SPEAKER_01]: Nothing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because investigation, dhamma's investigation, is... cannot be very painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Each kind of thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Think about these things through and through and through.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's painful in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't really know what to think about and how to think about, so then it requires... Once you know, then you will be able to tune in your effort, so it won't be a strain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just thinking about dhamma, you feel like you think, oh, I have to think about these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can say that, but basically it's more accurate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to discern this thing within what has already arisen, the dhammas that have already arisen.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to change the way of looking at what's already right in front of you all the time and you're not just about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not fabricating anything new.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just discerning within what's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's actually quite effortless.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because really your renunciation
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, just keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we're not in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That can involve some pain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Looking after your thoughts properly, keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's, you know, that can involve pain, of course.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even that involves the pain in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same as giving up any habits.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensual habits, in particular, cause the pain in the beginning, but then afterwards it doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: It involves the pain in the beginning, because you're just too dependent on
[SPEAKER_00]: Non-renunciation.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you stick with renunciation, then you recognize, well, actually, no, this is the natural state of things which...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the sensuality that requires the effort, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_00]: Renunciation doesn't require effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It requires the effort when your mind is still centered upon the sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: And same note, it requires the effort, but when you start discerning that that is the... that is the correct order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality is circumstantial, arisen on the basis of non-sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, it's sensuality that requires effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, by not engaging in sensuality, you're effortless, no burden on you, no pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then your mind just won't go to sensuality, because that's that which needs effort, not the current state.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that wouldn't have happened if you haven't been emulating the current state beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you haven't been emulating the non-sensuality beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's just without all the other more important benefits of not exposing yourself to danger and admire and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: And this wall